so now we have seen that in MSI even
when we have an intervention we need to
write to memory every time we have a
cache to cach transfer so for example C1
has the Block in the M State cuz it just
wrote it C2 wants to read the data so it
puts a read request on the bus C1
responds with the data so now C2 has the
data but C1 can no longer just write to
this block so C1 gets the block in the
shared State C2 gets the Block in the
shared State and that's why the memory
had to grab the data when C1 was
responding now what can happen is C2
writes so it sends an invalidation cuz
it already has the data now C1 gets
invalid State C2 gets the modified State
and then let's say this read write
Behavior moves to another core like C1
so pretty much if one core reads and
writes then another one reads and writes
and so on we can have a repetition of
this so pretty much the data is kind of
moving around the caches but the problem
is every time it moves between caches
the memory also gets written and the
memory doesn't have as much bandwidth as
the caches do so the problem really is
that here we needed to do a memory right
another problem occurs because when C2
has written for example and has the data
in the modified State and then C2
responds with data and that causes a
memory right we again get C1 has the
Block in shared State C2 has the Block
in shared State now if C3 reads because
both of these have the Block in the
shared State the memory provides the
data so we have memory reads here even
though one of these could have responded
with the data if we only knew which of
the two should respond definitely both
of them should not respond so if we had
the way to tell which one of them should
respond we could avoid this memory read
by the one that is responsible for
responding providing the data as long as
there are new requesters this can happen
a lot of times so if another core reads
same thing we get the memory read
although now there are three cores with
the data in the shared State and so on
we want to avoid the update to memory as
long as there is a cache that still
holds the most recent value of the block
and we want to avoid memory reads if
there is a cache that can provide this
block because again memory bandwidth is
a lot lower than cash bandwidth and also
memory reads and wrs are a lot more
expensive in terms of power and latency
than cach reads and wrs but to do this
we need to make a non-modified version
of the Block in one of the caches
responsible for giving data to other
caches when they want it so that the
memory doesn't need to respond and
eventually writing the block to memory
so that the memory doesn't need to be
updated every time we do something like
this so what we really need to know is
which of the shared copies is the one
responsible and we will know this by
introducing another state called o which
stands for owned so there will be one
owner of the block if others are sharing
it the O state will behave just like the
shared State except that whenever there
is a request for the data in the block
the owner is the one of the sharers that
gets to respond and also if the owner
replaces the block from the cache it
gets to write back to memory so that we
ensure that memory gets updated